A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Series A FA310
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Series A
1819-1968 1910-1931
Rockefeller Archive Center
Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine)
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Spelman Fund
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
Rockefeller University
Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Rockefeller, John D.
General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller, Winthrop
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
Sealantic Fund, New York
Spelman family
Standard Oil Company
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Rockefeller Foundation
Rockefeller, David
Rockefeller family
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
International Education Board
China Medical Board (U.S)
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Davison Fund
FA310
76 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Scope and Contents note
This series consists of all material relating to John D. Rockefeller that could not be placed in the John D. Rockefeller papers (FA002) due to limitations of date and type of material. Of special interest are the correspondence files, including those related to boards, the Rockefeller family, and investments; and the files on the Forest Hill, Golf House, and Pocantico Hills properties.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include:
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Arts; Business; Art, Modern; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Economic development; Art; Economics; Economic policy; Education -- United States; Education; Federal government -- United States; Family planning; Government policy; Folk art; Health insurance; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Housing rehabilitation; Public relations; Public welfare; Religion; Religious institutions; Restoration and conservation; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Travel; United States; Urban policy; Urban renewal; World War I; World War II; Medical research; Medical education; New York (N.Y.); Medical sciences; Parks -- New York (State); New York (State); Performing arts; Philanthropy -- United States; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Public health; Prohibition; Public policy; Public health administration; Business enterprises, Foreign; Philanthropy; Capital investments; Charitable contributions; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charities; Charities -- Investments; Child welfare; Civic improvement; International cooperation; International economic relations; International education; International relations; International relations -- United States; Juvenile delinquency; Maternal health services; Medical care; Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth); Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Spelman Fund; Mauze, Abby Rockefeller; Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Center; Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich; Rockefeller, John D.; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, Winthrop; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Sealantic Fund, New York; Spelman family; Standard Oil Company; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller, David; Rockefeller family; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; International Education Board; China Medical Board (U.S); Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); Davison Fund
- Addresses, 1904, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  "Early Experiences of a Young Business Man," first given on May 7, 1904. A second speech from 1918.
- Autograph (Box 1, Folder 0001A)
- Biographical Data - Correspondence, 1927-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Magazine and newspaper articles; affidavits by two Tioga residents re: John D. Rockefeller's birthplace.
  Related Archival Materials note
  See also Box 67, Folders 6-8.
- Biographical Data - Correspondence, 1942-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Magazine and newspaper articles. Attempt by Mrs. Dwelle to sell recollections of John D. Rockefeller by Langdon refused by John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
- Birthday, 1912-1918, 1926-1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Party plans, announcements to press, friendly letters; Inglis acted as press representative. 1932 movie statement re: depression. Correspondents include Fannie Evans, Robert W. Gumbel.
- Birthday, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Birthday - Letters, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Birthday - Major Bowes's Radio Talk, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Birthday - Newspaper Articles - By Town (A-M), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Birthday - Newspaper Articles - By Town (N-W), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Birthday - Letters, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Letters wishing John D. Rockefeller a happy birthday; family telegrams.
- Birthday - Newspaper Articles - By Town (A-K), 1935 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Birthday - Newspaper Articles - By Town (L-Y), 1935 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Birthday - Gifts, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Distribution of presents received.
- Birthday - Letters, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Gifts and birthday wishes from strangers; gifts were returned. Some family telegrams; John D. Rockefeller's telegrams to family and friends.
- Birthday - Newspaper Articles - By Town (A-K), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  John D. Rockefeller, Jr. acknowledgements to editors for articles and editorials about John D. Rockefeller's 97th birthday.
- Birthday - Newspaper Articles - By Town (L-S), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Birthday - Newspaper Articles - By Town (U-Y), 1936 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Birthday - 100th Anniversary, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Consideration of memorial radio program; letters to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
- Checkbooks, 1919-1933 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Christmas - Cards/Gift Lists, 1904-1929 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Lists of John D. Rockefeller's Christmas gifts to family, friends, and employees.
- Christmas - Cards/Gift Lists, 1930-1936 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Christmas - Cards (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Christmas - Thank You Letters, 1934-1936 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Clark & Rockefeller; Clark, Gardner & Company; Rockefeller, Andrews and Flagler - Miscellaneous, 1860-1870 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Correspondence - Abbott, E. J. - Adams, M. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Abbott, E. J., June 24, 1931. Loan request.Abbott, Eugene B., October 20, 1924. Death of Jonathan P. Abbott.Abercrombie, A. Lincoln, March 1, 1926. Baptist Church in Florida.Acheson, M. W., Jr., November 1929. Shadyside Academy dormitory to honor Dr. J. M. Richmond.Acker, Ida A., April 1929. On death of Joseph A. Acker.Acker, Joseph H., September 6, 1923. Thanks for water and coal.Adams, Almeda C., 1919 - 1931. Blind music teacher in Cleveland. Small Rockefeller gifts. Problems. Trip to Europe.Adams, Charles E., June 1926, March 1931. Condolences.Adams, Mrs. Crosby, January - February 1929. Thanks for her book on Hymnology.Adams, Edgar E., June 1923, February 1931. Reminiscences of "old times", good work of pastor.Adams, Marcia Rockefeller (Mrs.), March 24, 1927. Relative asking for aid.Adams, Mamie (Mrs.), February 18, 1931. Greetings.
- Correspondence - Adams, U. L. - Allen, Paul Jr. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  Adams, Usher, L., and Grace F. Adams (Mrs.), 1930 - 1930. Cleveland homeopathic physician. Visits. Rockefeller gifts. Condolence.Aitken, Margaret, June 30, 1923. Thank you on behalf of class for visit to Pocantico Hills.Akers, Albert M., 1930; 1931. Seasons Greetings.Albert, King of the Belgians, 1919 - 1920. John D. Rockefeller given Cordon of Leopold II.Albertson, Alta, 1924; 1927 - 1928. Thanks for dimes; inquiry on book title.Albertson, G. V., March 1922. Sunday school appeal.Aldrich, Larry, December 22, 1922. Christmas greetings.Aldrich, Mr. and Mrs. Stuart M., c. July 31, 1929. Wedding invitation.Aldrich, Winthrop A., February - March 1921. Condolence on death of son.Alexander, Charles B. (Mrs.), February 1927. Condolence on death of Charles B. Alexander.Alexander, Edmonia, (Mrs.), March 1929. Mental patient sends gift.Alexander, W. H., August 1927, c. 1930. Would accept long-ago given invitation to visit; wedding invitation.Allen, Augustus N., 1924; 1930. $100 note of 1895 to John D. Rockefeller; Baptist Home Aid.Allen, Mrs. Charles J., April 1929. Asks for copies of poem.Allen, Frances, M., October 1928. For book dealer, think John D. Rockefeller liked to buy books for Euclid Baptist Church members.Allen, Ida, December 11, 1928. Ask aid for another.Allen, John K., 1929 - 1930. Memorial window for.Allen, Paul, September 1928.Allen, Paul, Jr., November 12, 1928. Thank you. Requests letter of introduction for son (family document).
- Correspondence - Allwendinger, H. - Andrews, H. E. (Mrs.) (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Allwendinger, Helene, October 6, 1923. Visited Forest Hill.Alnutt, John L., June 1926. Asks that old Rockefeller home be restored.Alston, William J., 1928 -1929. Cleveland barber, shaved John D. Rockefeller, a student of Laura Spelman Rockefeller in grammar school.Althouse, Clara L., 1930. Visit.Alward, Grace, (Mrs.), May 26, 1927; 1930. House at Pocantico Hills.Ambrose, Edith M., 1919 - 1921. Golf visit, birthday.American Petroleum Institute, 1925. John D. Rockefeller gift for scientific research in oil industry, $250,000.American Tract Society, 1930. Distributed John D. Rockefeller poem.Ames, Adelbert, 1921, 1926 - 1931. Exchange of gifts and greetings.Ames, Mr. and Mrs. Oakes, c. June 1926. Marriage invitation.Ami, Henry, 1930. Gift of book.Amundsen Expedition, June 1922. Request for aid.Anderson, Martha, July 1927. Condolence.Anderson, D. L., December 22, 1928; January 10, 1930. Invitations to John D. Rockefeller.Anderson, M. E., (Mrs.), August 1929. John D. Rockefeller poem.Anderson, William S., June 23, 1931. Request for aid.Andrews, Horace E., December 3, 1918. Condolence.
- Correspondence - Andrews, John (Mrs.) and Zula A. Bachman, 1919-1928 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Mrs. John Andrews and daughter, Mrs. Zula A. Bachman. Widow of early business partner. Gifts. Tombstone for John Andrews, financial assistance.
- Correspondence - Andrews, W. E. - Arden School (Box 4, Folder 29)
  Andrews, Walter E., February - March 1930. Cleveland recollections.Andrus, George W., 1928. Commercial School, fellow alumnus.Angela, Mr. and Mrs. Francis - Wedding invitation, c. December 1926.Angell, Marion, November 29, 1926. Wedding gift to William R. McAlpin.Anti-Saloon League, 1919 - 1922, 1928 - 1929. John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gifts to League. Worldwide plan of 1920.Applegarth, Alice, May 9, 1927. Tioga recollections.Applegarth, Henry C., and daughter Margaret, 1919 - 1927. Baptist minister. Gifts. Visits.Appleton, Helena D., 1931. Visit.Archbold, John F., 1921; 1930. Condolences.Arden School, 1922 - 1926. Appeals for aid from Lakewood girls' school.
- Correspondence - Armington, W. B. - Austin, A. E. (Dr. and Mrs.) (Box 4, Folder 30)
  Armington, William B., April 4, 1921. Golf permit.Armstrong, Jesse J., March 10, 1920. Golf.Arrowsmith, Ella G., April 1923. Request for aid.Ashley, Henry D., December 1927. Request for aid.Ashmead, Charles A., 1918 - 1928. Gifts to minister in Tarrytown.Aten, Mr. and Mrs. Aaron P., June 12, 1922. Anniversary invitation.Atkins, Nat., 1922 - 1923. Visits to Pocantico Hills grounds.Atwater, William C., October 1922. Sends 1839 coin, golf.Atwood, Albert W., November 8, 1922. Writer.Auchincloss, Hugh D., (Mrs.), c. January 1928. Wedding invitation.Austin, Alonzo E., (Dr. and Mrs.) Sara Hull Austin, 1920 - 1931. Homeopathic physician. Gifts. Greetings. Drugs.
- Correspondence - Austin, C. A. - Avery, A. D. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  Austin, Chellis A., 1930. Death.Austin, George, January 16, 1929. Painting to be returned.Austin, Mrs. Samuel, April 2, 1924. Picture of John D. Rockefeller received.Automobiles, 1919 - 1920.Avery, Addie D., 1921 - 1930. South Dakota relations, Miles Avery Rockefeller line.
- Correspondence - Avery, Elroy M., 1920-1931 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  Family historian. Avery family graves and traditions. Miles Avery Rockefeller. Gifts.
- Correspondence - Avery, J. H. - Ayres, A. B. (Box 5, Folder 33)
  Avery, Jennie H., 1926; 1930. Overworked ministers.Avery, Rowena, 1921 - 1924. Monthly pledge to Aunt and daughter Mrs. Madeline Avery Livermore.Avery, Stephen, 1921 - 1928. Cemetery care.Ayers, E. L., August 1927. Offers chair as gift.Ayling, Charles F., 1924 - 1931. Golf.Ayres, Arthur B., 1923 - 1931. Oil man. Greetings. Visits.
- Correspondence (B), 1920-1931 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  Unknown correspondents.
- Correspondence - Babin - Ballard, E. L. (Box 5, Folder 35)
  Babin, (Mr.), December 31, 1921. Children's success.Babson, Roger W., June 1922. Asking for article.Bacheller, Irving, 1927; 1930 - 1931. Teacher, friend of John D. Rockefeller.Backus, H. M., 1919 - 1931. Illinois. Son of "Widow Backus". John D. Rockefeller gifts. Respect for John D. Rockefeller. Financial problems.Bagby, A. Paul, March 17, 1931. Thanks for visit.Baggett, B. B., December 1930. Committee membership declined.Baily, D. Algar, February 1929. Sending dime.Bainbridge, Lucy S. (Mrs.), July 30, 1923. Thanks for literature.Baker, Dorothy H., 1924. Thanks for flowers.Baker, George F., May 13, 1931. Eulogy of G. F. Baker.Baker, George F., Jr., May 1931. Condolence/thanks.Baker, Hal D., Jr., January 12, 1930. Asking for financial assistance.Baker, Walter E., September 30, 1929. Thanks for gift to Euclid church.Bakker, Cornelius N., January 4, 1927. Thanks for Christmas gift.Balch, Albert S., December 1927. Declines autograph.Baldwin, Mr. and Mrs. Arthur D., c. March 24, 1924. Wedding invitation.Baldwin, Fannie B. (Mrs.), February 27, 1922. Thanks for condolence.Baldwin, Henry R., December 14, 1921. Thanks for condolence.Baldwin, John F., 1930 - 1931. Catholic priest. Best wishes.Ballard, Edward L., 1921 - 1930. New York City. Fifth Avenue Baptist Church. Apples.
- Correspondence - Bancroft, M. - Bayne, S. G. (Box 5, Folder 36)
  Bancroft, Margaret, September 1925. Houseguest.Banks, C. E., (Mr. and Mrs.), February 15, 1928. Dime.Banks, Louis A., July 1929. Poem on John D. Rockefeller.Baptist Conventions, 1923; 1929. John D. Rockefeller gifts.Baptist Home for the Aged, 1916, 1920, 1923, 1930. John D. Rockefeller gifts to Baptist homes.Barbour, C., (President of Brown University), June 15, 1931. Invitation.Barbour, Clarence A., 1929. Memorial to Walter Rauschenbusch.Barbour, George H., June 1926. Sending picture.Barchi, Joseph P., 1930 - 1931. VFW post appeal.Barker, E. Frye, 1920. Death of F. J. Barnes.Barnard Group, 1923. "Adam & Eve". Requests to see statues; Barnard claims to have lost money making group.Barnes, Arthur, 1926 - 1931. Egg farm in Pocantico.Barnett, Mrs. Frank, July 20, 1927. Wants bus stop shelter.Barrett, Clarebelle, May 18, 1928. Asks for help for summer camp.Barrett, Frank, May 1929. Asks for interview.Barron, C. W., 1925 - 1926. Praise for John D. Rockefeller's business career.Barryville, New York Methodist Church, May 20, 1931. Appeal; tells of John D. Rockefeller 1902 $1.00 tip.Barstow, Lois B., (Mrs.), 1925; 1926. Invitations.Barstow, William A., 1922. Death.Bartoe, Annie L., January 1928. Send dime.Bartlett, Mary, February 2, 1920. Sends $100.Bassett, Helen W., (Mrs.), 1930. Selling book plates.Bassette, Elizabeth and Ann, February 6, 1929. Death of mother.Bassetts, Anne L., 1924. Regrets ride invitation.Batchellor, Stillman, September 22, 1930. Prunes for sale.Bates, Elmer, (Mrs.), March 18, 1925. Asks for loan.Bates, Laure M., 1921 - 1928. Work with deaf in Cleveland and St. Paul, appeals.Batta, John, Jr., July 19, 1928. Birthday.Battenfield, James E., November 27, 1930. Dimes.Bause, Louise, December 1924. Gift of $50.Baverstock, William (Mrs.), June 1925. Gift of $25.Bayne, Nanette, March 1925. Writing a book; seeks interview.Bayne, S. G., 1920 - 1921. Sends book on New York City.
- Correspondence - Beardsley, W. H. - Bellis, B. (Box 5, Folder 37)
  Beardsley, William H., December 1925. Death.Beatty, Lou E., February 4, 1924. Asks for aid.Beatty, Mabel, (Mrs.), March 22, 1930. Appeal.Beaven, Albert W., October, 1929. Invitation - Colgate - Rochester Divinity School.Beckman, Fred, (Mr. and Mrs.), 1921; 1927. Cared for at Institute.Beckman, Mrs. Helen, 1924 - 1930. Ithaca, New York. Gifts to cousins. Old age. Family problems.Bedford, Alfred C., 1920 - 1925. Praise for John D. Rockefeller's business career.Bedford, E. T., 1920 - 1928. New York City. Standard Oil news. Birthday wishes.Bedford, Frederick H., 1927 - 1931. Standard Oil man; retirement, death.Beemer, D. S., July 23, 1927. Birthday greetings from post of Grand Army of the Republic.Behrens, John D. Rockefeller, II, February 22, 1926. Dimes.Behring, Mr. and Mrs. Pehr C., January 7, 1928. Wedding invitation.Beland, Henry B., March 1927. Requests for interview.Bell, John C., March 1929. Denies newspaper story about poor stomach.Bell, Graddy B., December 1929. Re: Copy of "Sohioan" with articles on John D. Rockefeller.Bell, H. E., December 30, 1925. Petroleum research.Bell, N. S., (Mrs.), July - August, 1928. Looking for job.Belle, Josephine, November - December 1925. Wedding gift.Bellinger, Mrs. Floyd, February 27, 1930. Relative asking for money.Bellis, Berton, April 1927. Sending poems.
- Correspondence - Benavedes, E. - Biggar, F. E. (Box 5, Folder 38)